so anyway that's
what you were speaking about today yesterday
how to practice summer time
not to calm down in regards the breath
the well especially because we talk
as i said we talk a lot about the right
endurance and sense restraint
and every gradual um every description
of the gradual training in the sutures
starts starts with that so you won't be
doing proper samadhi unless you're fully
proper samadhi unless you're fully
restrained uh curbed
and and self-controlled so that is a
like seeing the danger in the slightest
fault then
not following things with eyes ears nose
and so on
and eating in moderation exactly and
then that leads to the
kind of watchfulness and then somebody
and so on
so but it might create an impression
that okay so it's just about endured
students a lot it's about endurance but then
a lot it's about endurance but then
there is a point where you can come
calm within the endurance calm yourself
within the endurance so then
and you the same endurance is not
unpleasant that that patient endurance as the
that that patient endurance as the
foremost austerity
it does not need to be felt unpleasantly
and that's the that's the difference in
the um
in the suttas when it talks about the um
like maha magalana his way to
enlightenment was quick and pleasant
as in it didn't take long because he was
the master of
of of the right samatha the right
calming so although he went through the same
so although he went through the same
process of you know abandoning kiles
and everything else that would make
people go mad for him he didn't feel any
displeasure because his mind was so
so unshakable sariputa on the other hand
the form was in wisdom after the buddha
he said his way was
long and unpleasant so he had to endure
more pain
that on the kind of that patient
endurance of course he still had samadhi
in janus and so on and when he did he
became enlightened
so the role of that samatha which often
goes with vipassana
is obviously significant and crucial in
a way
but as as i was always saying you can't
meditate rightly
unless you have the right view that
statement can be a bit too abstract for
people so practically the reason why you won't
so practically the reason why you won't
be meditating rightly
without a right view is because your
meditation your samata will not be calming of the
your samata will not be calming of the
endurance it will be rooted in aversion
towards endurance
it will be rooted in you trying to get
rid of the discomfort
of endurance through this meditation
technique and means you don't endure which means
and means you don't endure which means
you're ignoring
well you're blocking the direction
through which some other would work
calm you and make your way to
enlightenment pleasant like your
endurance please make sure so endurance is not
please make sure so endurance is not
negotiable
how much you're going to suffer on
account of it how much your mind will be
tormented yeah that depends on individual
yeah that depends on individual
depending on your faculties if you're
more about
like a person aside or if you're more
about calming down but it needs to be
done that's why again gradual way always
that's why again gradual way always
starts
by sila seeing the danger in the
slightest fault
full sense restraint not giving into
centrality acting out of ill will
distraction moderation eating
results in watchfulness results in
buildup of endurance and now within that
you can learn what calmness is what true
summative is but not at the expense or not like oh
is but not at the expense or not like oh
i'll deal with endurance the pain of it
i'll deal with the discomfort i'll
manage it
because for most people without a right
view that's what meditation is
which means just becomes another
management another cover-up that's
rooted in aversion
towards discomfort and you're not
uprooting anything
so one is enduring
not giving in to any defilements
and the pressure is there
pressuring pressure pressure but you're
not giving in you're not giving it
there you go that's your endurance then
again you have a pressure and that's why
it's pressure like
but just you know do this or do that
in order to get rid of the pressure so
you see that you feel that whatever
you'll be doing
you'll be acting you know to get rid of
the pressure so while you're all full of
doubt conflicted giving in or refusing to give
conflicted giving in or refusing to give
in tempted pressured
enduring the pain what else is there
that you are kind of aware of and you
can be aware of
and it's enduring and you're doing it
and it doesn't require effort
and it doesn't require special intention
and it cannot become
um something you do in order to get rid
of this or that because it's just too
subtle of an action
what is there happening while you're all
tormented with the pressure you're not
giving in
breathing in breathing out that's what's
happening
so that's why it's the the anapanasati
uh whenever described it's like he knows
like knowingly he breathes in knowingly
so it's about the knowledge of your
breath that it's already there
happening to the body so to speak so
that's what we speak that's what we say
like um the uh the peripheral
so it's not like okay so you might you
might even like you know if you're all
wound up
through that endurance and sense is
pressuring you and so on you might feel
like okay so breathing like this or breathing
okay so breathing like this or breathing
like yeah whatever do it but at the same
time just know that you can only do that
just know that you can only do that
because the breath is already there
breathing so it's effortless it's that's
why it's a neutral action
it's an action that cannot truly if you
see it in that
peripheral sense like if you just know
it not necessarily do it
because you don't need to do it in order
to breathe you're already breathing
while you're trying to do all these
other things including enduring getting
rid of the endurance and so on
so that's why oh all i need to do i
don't need to do this in order for it to
be
the action that will calm me down all i
need to do is know it
happening underneath whatever's going on
here mindfulness of reading because it's
mindfulness of reading because it's
underneath already
so that's what means put it first put it
before whatever else you're occupied
with not in response to not at the
expense of
and so on and even now while we are
talking breathing is there and you can know even
breathing is there and you can know even
while you're talking that you're still
breathing in breathing out you don't
need to control
it you need to stop it i don't need to
stop am i breathing i know i'm breathing
however vaguely there is still the
thread of the knowledge of the same breath
of the knowledge of the same breath
breathing in breathing out
so is that thread of that peripheral
knowledge that doesn't require any
action just pure recognition that's how you
just pure recognition that's how you
start to practice
in the right direction as a just
something you're aware of that's there
you're not doing it in response to this
it's there happening and you just choose
to not forget it
that's it within this pressure or
whatever else
and if you cultivate sufficiently enough
that not forgetting of the breath
recollectedness of the breath
mindfulness of the breath that's why
it's satay
it will come down any hindrance that was
there occupying you or pressuring you
he will take away that um
first person like engagement with this
pressure and this hindrance and i must
do this same as this
and it's just things will be just seen
for what they are and during their
neither pleasant nor unpleasant
neutral and that itself would be very
pleasant obviously because you just
relieve yourself of pressure without
trying to get rid of it
and that's the true summit and then like
oh yeah that's something you can do
because you have the right view now that
prevents you from trying to manage at
any expense
that recognizes within the endurance i
need to find the calmness
and that will then force you in the
direction of what true calmness is
so you know there's an in-breath and out
breath an action that is within my
experience and pretty much fundamental for any
and pretty much fundamental for any
other action i do it precedes it
structurally so to speak
like i can stand up walk talk all of
that requires
breathing to be there
and that's how you count the sankara the
the determination of the body
through calming the determination of the
body which is in and out of breath
all your bodily actions will come down
or the pressures those bodily actions
will come down
and there's a similar they said that on
a panasonic when practiced made much of
you know when you become proficient and
it properly through that
well through that non-management by the
direction of calming of your pressure
through it
uh it's like the rain they would sort of
clean the air of all the dust particles
but you can't emphasize enough the the
point that like
if you're doing it as a technique as a
method as something you're doing
adhering focusing hard in front of you you're
focusing hard in front of you you're
doing it at the expense
of your container of endurance that you
have developed you're doing it as
an escape means you're doing it because
you you reverse
there was discomfort of it and that's
why you're doing it wrong
that's why it's just the extension of
centrality because what what else is the
principle of centrality
is underlying tendency to aversion it
turns you towards getting rid of it by
the means of
anything that's not as averse or more
pleasant that's that's the principle of
that's that's the principle of
centrality that's where people go to
central desires and so on
and would have said that when when a
ignoble mind is touched
by an unpleasant feeling doesn't know
any other escape doesn't know any other
calming in regard to the discomfort they endures
in regard to the discomfort they endures
other than turning towards sensuality
but each time they turn to sensuality
more of the underlying tendency because
of which they were suffering on account
of the original
discomfort will increase
and then the underlying tendency for
depending on more pleasure will also
increase so the more you give in to the direction
so the more you give in to the direction
of trying to manage get rid of your pain
get rid of the suffering through
replacing it through any more pleasant
experience well the worse it gets like scratching
well the worse it gets like scratching
the edge
so that's the whole point of sila sense
restraint virtue moderation watchfulness it's
virtue moderation watchfulness it's
exactly that
to provide you container they will not
go to centrality
they will reveal and literally what you
are what you are
averse to it's no one's fault
it's the setup of the aggregates the
setup of the senses
they are basically well
they're not pleasant in themselves let's
put it that way
having a body is a chore having senses
is it's it's it's it's this resistance
natural resistance that you are paired
with and you have to endure whether you
and you have to endure whether you
wanted or not so that's what like
see you're not born with all this like a
newborn baby doesn't have all this
proliferationality but it has set up of
the senses
that in themselves are pressuring
unpleasant resisting ignorance
resisting ignorance
ignorant mind and that means automatic
direction towards pleasure avoiding this
and that's that's the word would refer
to the newborn babies that has the same
underlying tendencies that's why we
become the minded dependent on sensuality that
the minded dependent on sensuality that
doesn't want pain so so your um
patient endurance your seal or somebody
is about to
containing you trying to spill out the
world's senses
at the expense of the senses that are
kind of unendurable also it feels
so that's why we said oh you need to
find a different type of pleasure
um john you that's what we'll say you
need to find a different type of
pleasure than that of senses
or you could say a different type of
calming than that
peace that you get to satisfy your
desires
in order to lose any attraction towards
sensuality and
a prude deal will and by the way that's
also why your will is paired with it
you are already averse towards your own
sense basis
neutrality is the aversion because they
are unpleasant
if you don't endure that aversion if you
don't calm yourself in regard to the
aversion of your own senses
you go out there for pleasure which
means you will go out there
for any other kind of um that aversion
will proliferate with you with you going
out there with the pleasure
so people have ill will towards other
people because fundamentally they carry
a will towards their own senses
that's the root of every real world and
because of the aversion towards their
own senses
they are dependent on sensuality through
other people and in the world
it's the same route so you approve that
route of a version towards your own
senses and
uh you have lost any central desire or
any will towards anywhere
anywhere in the world that doesn't make
the sense as comfortable no
no no just makes your mind go beyond
this that basic discomfort of the senses that
that basic discomfort of the senses that
you never ever addressed because
from the moment you were born you your
mind was
going in the direction of the world to
avoid again that's where people feel boredom
again that's where people feel boredom
boredom just brings back that which
you've been out running from the day one
the discomfort of your senses that are
truly uncomfortable
so samata is when you stop giving in
blindly and holding views
that are about management of that
discomfort some of this calming of that discomfort
some of this calming of that discomfort
after you have endured it efficiently
enough and develop clarity in regard to
it
so calming the discomfort within the how
do you commit well any
any satikitana would calm it but it
might be too abstract like you know how
my body is here or something to my
activity of breath that it's there all
the time
from the day one as well and it kind of
precedes the senses
it doesn't require your senses in order
to breathe
so if you cultivated make much of your
breath as calming of the endurance that it's
as calming of the endurance that it's
not negotiable
that's around chip in half a night
seven days fortnight seven months or
seven years
at most because the only reason
you still depend on on you know
sensuality distraction and so on is
because you're still unable to endure the core
you're still unable to endure the core
of the problem which is
the census and that's when arahant in
the suttas
who becomes awakened he says oh
i've done all the work there's
absolutely no more resistance no more
loss towards anything everyone will
never concede nothing left
any disturbance that's left for me just
on a kind of this sixth sense body
that's left until it breaks apart
and that's no disturbance anymore
you're not actually the senses are kind
of
uncomfortable but they're not dukkha in
themselves it's your resistance
aversion to discomfort on the deepest
level of
me that's why even even brahmavihara's
as a practice starts with loving
kindness towards this
first and then from there towards
everybody else
because that's the root of the problem
this here is uncomfortable
and automatically that discomfort means
a version for me
there's not like i must get rid of the
senses i must kill this body i'm saying
well you're just going to send yourself
to who knows what other
you body it's it's it's a good
opportunity to actually just train
in regards to discomfort of the senses
and not being a verse towards it
through discovering calmness within it
because there is like eye of the storm
but it takes effort you need to develop
it and when you do
all of the all of the factors that
depend on the world and gone
mind is unmoved because that's what was
moving the mind the aversion towards
this thing that i don't want
nothing else everything else was
secondary you know all the wrong views and all the
you know all the wrong views and all the
sensuality it was all secondary rooted
in this
so that's the um the correct summertime